hello and welcome to this special
webinar of the opus legacy roundtable
series where we feature conversations
with iconic thought leaders and business
trailblazers brought to you in
partnership with standard chartered bank
and opus by prudential a dedicated high
net worth offering designed to meet your
wealth management and legacy planning
needs i'm melissa jack now each
conversation in the opus legacy
roundtable series explores various
aspects of crafting a legacy and the
motivations and inspirations behind it
in this evening's conversation we'll
explore the idea of longevity something
that's both appealing and daunting now
it's appealing because the will to live
is a natural instinct for humans or any
sentient being for that matter it's also
daunting because longevity also means
being old and having all the problems
that come with aging but apparently
longevity need not equate aging
is there a difference and if there is
what is it and what does it mean for us
our family and society well this topic
is becoming increasingly important
because we're all living together or
we're all living longer than ever before
now in singapore we have one of the
highest life expectancy rates in the
world at nearly 84 years and this number
is continuing to rise but increasing
lifespans come with challenges
now prudential's latest research
reimagining 100 shows that more than two
in three singaporeans are not prepared
for their rising longevity from a health
and wealth perspective to learn more
about how we can truly make the most of
our longer lives we'll be joined by
global expert on longevity and the aging
society professor andrew j scott dialing
in from the uk now andrew is professor
of economics at london business school
he has previously held posts at harvard
university london school of economics
and oxford university among several
other appointments he is also a
best-selling author his book the 100
year life is a number one bestseller in
japan his latest book is the new long
life now the financial times calls it a
manifesto for better later years that is
essential reading for policy makers and
chief executives
now for the first part of tonight's
conversation andrew will spend some time
sharing his perspective on longevity and
how we can start crafting a future full
of possibilities for ourselves and our
loved ones and for the second part we'll
go deeper into this topic with andrew
where you will also have the opportunity
to ask him your questions before we
conclude
well andrew thank you for being with us
today now as you begin your talk andrew
perhaps a quick question to set it off
now from what i could tell you began
really really focused on longevity and
aging society only in the last what 10
to 15 years so what was the catalyst for
you to dive deeper into this topic
yeah great question melissa so i guess
there's two parts one is professional
and the other is personal
the professional is i've always liked
ideas that have an impact and impact
doesn't come bigger for me than
longevity um but also on a personal
level and by the way as a trend i think
people have misunderstood it so it's
great to talk about something really
important that touches each of us where
everyone else doesn't really get it
right but also there was a personal side
which is i was a little bit bored doing
what i'd always done talking about
interest rates and exchange rates i
wanted to do something different and of
course that's one of the features of a
long life how we actually progress and
change our identity from one thing to
another
it was also something else which was i
had three children
and in particular my middle child louis
was just graduating and he said dad i'm
not going to get a job i'm going to take
a couple of years out
and i was sort of quite angry about that
actually i was worried and i was angry
but the more i thought about things and
thought about
why he was behaving differently from my
generation and the parents generation
the more it got me thinking about
longevity and how we use the extra time
that these longer lives bring so a
mixture of the personal and the
profession
so what i want to try and do is uh talk
get you understand what longevity is
and give you a different perspective on
what is often called an aging society so
that's really what i'm about
and let me just begin though with the
aging society because this is the the
dominant narrative and obviously
singapore is an extraordinary example
around the world every country is seeing
two things a fall in the birth rate uh i
think it's like 1.3 children now per
female in singapore
and more people living longer
and you combine those two things
together you have smaller younger
cohorts and you have
larger older cohorts so there's more
older people and the average age of
society is increasing and this is
happening everywhere around the world
what marks out singapore is how quickly
these trends have happened and how
dramatic they are but around the world
we're seeing a rising proportion of
older people and that's what this slide
shows you here globally you know the
fastest growing age group in the world
is people aged over 100
but everywhere we're seeing more people
aged over 65 more people aged over 85
and this is called an aging society
and not always very positively you know
the notion is that old people are a
problem they don't work they get ill
they need a pension they have poor
health
i think that's a rather negative way of
looking at it i think we should be
celebrating
uh morning fewer children
losing fewer parents in mid-life and
more grandparents meeting their
grandchildren now as i mentioned with
the day going from 24 to 32 hours this
is really about time
so let's do a following thought
experiment let's ignore the first 20
years of life
let's ignore the last 10 years of life
i'll give you an evenings to rest i'll
give you the weekends but everything
else
i'm going to call productive hours
time you could spend
doing something
well if you live to 70
you have 125 000 hours
if you live to a hundred
you have two hundred and twenty thousand
productive hours you have another
hundred thousand productive hours and
that basically is the exam question that
we're all being asked what do you want
to do with that extra hundred thousand
hours
it's not about end of life it's about
all of life
how do you spend that extra hundred
thousand hours do you just spend more
time doing the same thing or do you look
to do new challenges and you develop new
skills and take on new identities
because key to a long life is having a
sense of purpose and a sense of
engagement but we will have to work for
longer if we're living for longer in the
100-year life book uh melissa mentioned
earlier we say well actually how do i
think about
responding to this extra time how do i
construct my life
and i want you to think about two groups
of assets
so on the left-hand side there's your
financial assets as an economist and i
think about money and a longer life
requires me to save more because i'm
probably going to be living longer and i
need more resources
and that's why we have to work longer
so there's the financial assets
but it would be a terrible mistake just
to focus on those
because we've also got to focus on our
intangible assets
let me just come back to the financial
assets you know i do some calculations
and if you're going to be living to a
hundred
you're probably going to work until
you're 80. but have a look at that
intangible assets
and there's three key types of
intangible assets the first is your
skills and knowledge
you've got to keep investing in those so
you can't rely upon working in your 70s
on what you learned in your 20s lifelong
learning is key
then there's your vitality assets that's
your mental and physical health as well
as your friends and relationships you've
got to be investing in those all the
time again if you just work for 60 years
what's that going to do to your mental
and physical health what does that do
for your relationships you've got to be
investing in these all the way through
your life then there's something we call
your transformational assets which is
your ability to deal with change change
that either you choose or is forced upon
you i want to change my career i've got
to change my career because technology
has taken no
and in a longer life you're going to
have to be better at dealing with these
transitions
and in the 20th century we created a
three-stage life education work
retirement
and what we're sort of doing is just
stretching out that second stage making
people work for longer by pushing out
the retirement date
but have a look at that intangible
assets
there's three key types of intangible
assets the first is your skills and
knowledge
you've got to keep investing in those
so you can't rely upon working in your
70s on what you learned in your 20s
lifelong learning is key
then there's your vitality assets that's
your mental and physical health as well
as your friends and relationships you've
got to be investing in those all the
time again if you just work for 60 years
what's that going to do to your mental
and physical health what does that do
for your relationships you've got to be
investing in these all the way through
your life
then there's something we call your
transformational assets which is your
ability to deal with change change that
either you choose or is forced upon you
i want to change my career i've got to
change my career because technology has
taken me away
and in a longer life you're going to
have to be better at dealing with these
transitions
if you put all these things together
what you realize is that we can't
respond to longer lives just by
stretching out that three-stage life
just by working longer and retiring
later
instead we see a multi-stage life begin
to emerge
a multi-stage life is one of many
careers and different changes and
transitions
sometimes working very hard focused on
money other times recharging a better
work back balance giving you the scope
to work on your health or your
relationships or perhaps doing something
with the community and being something
more social entrepreneur
so that three-stage life of education
work and retirement is beginning to
break out break up this is a big mindset
change for parents i talked about my own
son earlier on because we're so keen on
our children to be successful we
force-feed them into this three-stage
life but for all of us whether you're 20
50 or 80 this multi-stage life is
emerging
if you're in your mid-40s and you're
going to be working to your mid-70s
you've got more work ahead of you than
you've done already
that's a real sort of big change that
comes then with longevity what do i want
to do how do i prepare myself am i bored
of what i do what is the thing that
really excites me how do i make sure
that i influence how we age
we mustn't focus on chronological age
that's sort of how many candles there
are on my birthday cake
you've got to focus i would say on two
other things one is biological age
what is my health and make sure that
you're as healthy as possible for as
long as possible
it's very interesting developments
happening in that space but also what i
call prospective age
because really what matters is not the
number of candles in your cake but how
many more cakes you're going to have and
at every age you can now expect more
birthday cakes
in the 20th century we invented life
insurance
so that was a world where because many
people died in middle age you had life
insurance they made sure that your
family was protected financially if you
died in middle age
now there's something else around
we have to have longevity insurance
because a really big challenge we face
with these longer lifes
is outliving our wealth
outliving our health
outliving our skills
outliving our sense of purpose and
outliving our sense of relationships we
have to keep investing not just in our
finances in our skills our health our
relationships in this long life you want
to be healthy and always have a sense of
purpose
the new imperative is to age well
if for the first time ever the young
will become the old the new health
imperative is to age well
i heard a lot of talk about the silver
economy looking after older people it's
very important but even more important
is what i call the evergreen economy
making sure we age well
will all of us be prepared to spend
money to be looked after when we're old
but we'll spend even more money making
sure we age well
education pharmaceuticals food and drink
exercise leisure this is the evergreen
economy that's going to start to die
prudential actually had done some
research the latest that i see is
something called reimagining 100
on singaporeans that i understand you
contributed your expert take to as well
i discusses the impact of the pandemic
on our well-being and longevity so
andrew maybe let me first catch everyone
up on some of the key findings before i
get your view on on them now the study
found right that on financial well-being
nearly half of those surveyed say it has
worsened since the pandemic began that's
on financial well-being now on mental
health more than a third feel that the
state of their mental health has become
worse in the past year now for about one
in four people they say that their
physical health has deteriorated as well
now in view of the worsening financial
and work related stress caused by the
pandemic it's perhaps unsurprising that
the quality of relationships has also
been affected
prudential's 2018 survey had nine in 10
people saying they were happy in their
most significant relationships but fast
forward to prudential's latest research
that number has dropped by about 30
percentage points from
92 to 62 percent that six in ten people
compared with nine in ten people before
who say they're happy with their
relationship so andrew as we compliment
the issue of
longevity what are the implications of
these pandemic findings
it's so interesting and what a
fascinating set of statistics
particularly the one about the
relationships
um
so let me just say a few things about
when the pandemic first started to sort
of happen back february march
in 2020 here am i an economist focusing
on longevity and there's a global
pandemic happening and i worry for my
own health my family and the world but i
also thought well no one is going to be
interested in longevity in the midst of
a pandemic
what is extraordinary is how the
interest in this topic has just
increased
and in particular the need to focus on
our health has really come to the
forefront the awareness of how many old
people we've got who have been
particularly vulnerable has been key
but also the recognition that our health
is not just physical it's also mental
and you know statistics you gave
obviously paint a disturbing picture of
quite extraordinary time but it has
almost i would say
help more and more people think well
what matters now it's also throwing up
new opportunities we keep talking about
a different work life balance
um but you know i think more and more
people have recognized that you know a
sense of place and a sense of
relationships are utterly
key
and for a lot of us that was what we got
from work but denied the ability to go
into work then they throw a spotlight on
what was happening locally so our
community and our homes and of course
they are the most important
relationships
you know i talked about those different
assets about how you make the most of a
long life
and how you can think of those assets as
redesigning how we live our life
the thing that comes through time and
time again
on studies of what makes for a good life
is its relationships it's creating the
space to love and to be loved so of
course those findings you've got there
around mental health and stress and the
pressure it put on relationships says
wow how do we rebuild that and i think
that's what's really important about
longevity and i would say technology
which in the new long life we bring
together ai and robotics and longevity
we've got to make sure that we focus on
the human with technology we've got to
make sure that we enable us as humans to
do the things that we're good at
and that's about actually connecting
with one another it's about empathy
and the danger of a hundred life is we
focus so much on building up the
financial assets
that the finances run our life but
really we want the finances to support
the life that we need
and so what is it that we need human
connection human connectivity and a
sense of community and those things can
become ever more important and i think
that's what covert has revealed so so
very strongly so we've got to think
about investing in a wide portfolio of
assets yes you need to invest in your
finances yes you need to invest in
skills and purpose but also health
mental health and relationships i think
i think it's really interesting that you
should um highlight especially
you know the importance of the
non-financial aspect i mean financial is
definitely very important and we will
get into that um afterwards i really
want to have time to talk about that um
but when we're talking about the
non-financial aspect like physical and
psychological health um there was a
study that i found between singapore's
ministry of health and the global
institute of health metrics and
evaluation that found that singaporeans
may be living longer but also spending
more time in ill health up to ten and a
half years right and when it comes to
nurturing psychological health a
prudential study found that singaporeans
also tend to put all their eggs into one
basket their family right so would you
say that investing in non-financial
matters might actually be the most
common oversight that people tend to
make when it comes to living longer
you know ageism is a very strange thing
because
you know
sexism i i'm probably not going to
change my gender ethnicity i'm not going
to change my ethnicity but every person
who's young is probably going to become
old so ageism is a really sort of is a
prejudice against your future self so
yes we absolutely have to tackle ageism
and we're actually realize it's not
really age that is the issue people of
all ages are just people so that's the
kind of the the way in which you i think
deconstruct this narrative but it's
certainly hard but as i say the key
thing i think is you can start with your
own actions
and not try and infer anything from
someone's chronological age as to what
they need or what they can do i think
that's very very limiting now um
financial planning we did say we want to
talk about that it's definitely a
critical cornerstone in preparing for
longer life expectancies
again i would like to cite a
prudential's findings in that they have
done really quite a lot of work on this
more than two and three singaporeans are
not prepared financially for their
rising longevity
where do you see are the common mistakes
or the kind of misconceptions people
tend to have when it comes to planning
financially for the future
so
you know there's so many issues here so
one would be
simply that we're just not very good at
planning for the future there's a
present bias in so many of our actions
and actually as life expectancy gets
longer that's a real challenge because
we need to learn a new skill how do i
plan for my future self but our survival
evolutionary is very very much about
meeting present needs
but when the first time ever the young
will become the old we have to try and
learn patience long-term perspective
and this is something we can learn but
it has to be taught so teaching
financial literacy teaching health
literacy all of these things are
important so so one problem is we're
just not very good at planning for the
future um another problem i have is most
people just aren't aware of these life
expectancy trends and there's a bunch of
reasons behind that including the fact
that most governments when they produce
their headline number of life expectancy
it's a very static view of life
expectancy
it doesn't involve any projections on
these life expectancy trends so most
people are just unaware of how long
they're likely to live for so that's two
very very real problems so how do you
overcome that well i think you know
there's there's a couple of things that
are a key i talk about financial
literacy
but we do need to try and get people to
save more
and that's really hard because most
people have very pressing financial
needs today
but i think this is where these auto
enrollment schemes are so important and
of course singapore and the central
provident fund but making sure that you
try and help people you know even if
it's a small amount of money
particularly when they're young
that money gets locked away for a long
term purpose is really key
but then the other thing i want to try
and sort of say is i find it interesting
as an economist because i will straight
away go to think about money
and i'm comfortable with numbers i'm
comfortable with compound interest but
most people
aren't and i think one of the problems
with the financial sector is it often
tries to tell people you must save more
money you must manage your funds
differently
but that's not actually what people buy
into
i think what's interesting to me
focusing on time and longevity is most
people are comfortable budgeting with
time every day i haven't got enough time
how do i use this time here and there
and if you point out that actually there
is this longer life people start
thinking well how do i structure that
time and that's when they then start
coming into the finances
and for me that sort of way to try and
get into financial planning finance is a
key
but the finances to support the life
that we want to have and if we can think
about the life we want to have we can
then infer a financial plan i think for
me that's the really big change that is
happening with finances
you do need to save more in a longer
life
you do need to plan your finances
differently but there's sort of a
convergence occurring with
wealth
and health i think purpose as well
so you know you cannot possibly think
about
your future finances without saying will
i have the health to be able to earn
money if i need to and will i have the
skills necessary to earn money as well
so the savings for the future isn't just
financial it's also your health and your
skills and of course that's important
too because if you haven't got the
health later on you won't be able to
spend the money in the way that you want
to so i think the really big trend is
this integration of fine of financial
health
and physical and mental health and
purpose and well-being
uh and that that is what i call that
longevity insurance how do i insure
myself against living too long
and that's about finances health skills
relationships and police
money is a way of giving yourself future
options and you have more future so
taking care of the finances is
absolutely key
but then there's your health
and you know the thing i think is really
important for all of us to understand is
to focus on age
age is backward looking it's about how
many years you've had
it's also forward-looking how many more
years to go
and what can you give your future self
making a best friend of your future self
is really really important so giving
your future self money
giving yourself health
giving yourself relationships and a
sense of purpose
well i hope tonight's conversation has
given you some inspiration and direction
on how you can better prepare for living
a longer life and building a more
valuable legacy
if you'd like to discuss your wealth and
legacy planning needs please get in
touch with your relationship manager
and for more details on opus by
prudential go to opus.prudential.com
dot sg i'm melissa yaga thank you for
joining this conversation brought to you
by standard chartered bank and opens by
prudential good night
you